Hello everyone.
Welcome back to the next lesson in our IELTS writing course.
Today we will learn another question type in Task 2, named two-part questions.
Sometimes the test doesn't just ask for your opinion,
it asks you two direct questions like, why is this happening?
And is it good or bad?
It can feel like doing two essays in one.
In this lesson, we will learn how to
break down these prompts using task analysis,
organize our ideas using a mind map,
and evaluate a sample essay to identify common band 5 mistakes.
Ready to master this question type?
Let's jump in.
Do you remember the three steps that
we have to do before writing any essay?
Three seconds for you.
The three steps pre-writing are,
one, task analysis, two, brainstorming, three, outline.
First, let's move on to task analysis.
I'll give you 30 seconds to analyze the question and find three components.
Topic words, micro-topic words, and instruction words.
Have you finished?
We have, topic-words, people choosing to live by themselves.
Micro-topic words, increasing rapidly.
Instruction words, why is this the case?
Is this a positive or negative development?
We have understood that we need to write
about the rapid increase in the number of people living alone.
We can also see that we have to address two main questions.
So can you tell me, each question or
part in the instruction words reminds you of which question type we learned in the previous lessons?
And what do we need to do to answer them?
You'll have 15 seconds.
With the question, why is this the case?
It reminds us of the causes affect solutions question.
Here, we need to provide some reasons for the topic.
And with the question, is this a positive or negative development?
It reminds us of the advantages and disadvantages question.
Here, we need to give an opinion on
whether the topic is a positive or negative
development based on presenting the advantages and disadvantages.
So in general, two-part questions require you to address two parts of the questions.
Each part is similar to a question type that you have learned.
After finishing task analysis, let's move on to the next part, brainstorming.
In this course, we have learned three techniques for brainstorming ideas.
Listing, mind mapping, and 6Ws.
And please note that based on each question type,
you should choose the appropriate technique for them.
In the lessons on causes affect solutions and
advantages-disadvantages questions, we already used mind mapping.
So for this sample, we'll continue using mind mapping to brainstorm ideas.
Now I'm going to show you a mind map
with the central idea, higher number of
people living by themselves, and three main branches.
Reasons to brainstorm ideas for question 1, Advantages, and Disadvantages.
These two branches are for question 2.
Now please pause the video for three minutes
to add more branches and complete this mind map.
Have you finished?
Let me show you the mind map that I've created.
To know more about how to create this mind map,
you can read the PDF file attached below.
For now, let's move on to part 2, sample evaluation.
Firstly, let's read the following sample essay.
Next, let's move on to its outline.
Let's identify if this essay achieves band 5
or band 6 for task response and coherence
and cohesion, based on the following checklists.
First, let's start with task response.
This essay has met all the requirements except
for number 2, because there are only 207 words.
And number 6.
We will analyse this together and give some
solutions in part 3, sample improvements.
Let's continue with the checklist for coherence.
The essay only fully meets the requirement 6 of the conclusion.
For the others, the essay only meets parts of them.
Let's continue with the checklist for cohesion.
The second requirement has been met, but the first hasn't yet.
In the next part, sample improvements, we'll find
out why some boxes are not ticked and
see how to analyse and improve it.
And that brings us to the end of today's lesson.
We have successfully explored how to break down
two-part questions, organised our ideas using
a mind map, and critiqued a sample essay to spot common pitfalls.
As we saw, even if your ideas are good,
simple mistakes like falling under the word count
or failing to fully explain your points
can drag your score down to a band 5.
Now that you know what to look for,
make sure to check your own practice essays
against these requirements to ensure you are hitting that band 6 target.
Thank you for joining me and happy writing!